A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Francis X. Sutton FA568
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Francis X. Sutton
1949-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sutton, Francis X. (Francis Xavier)
Ford Foundation
FA568
30.53 Cubic Feet 79 boxes (2 legal sized)
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program in 1951 to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education in developing countries through overseas grants. During a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program merged with the International Training and Research and the Population programs to form a unified International Division. In July 1954, Francis X. Sutton joined the Ford Foundation as an Executive Associate in the Behavioral Sciences program. He become Assistant to the Vice President of the newly created International Division in February 1967 and in October of the following year, was promoted to Deputy Vice President of the division, a position he retained until his retirement in 1983. The Office Files of Francis X. Sutton span from 1949-2002 and document his tenure as a Program Associate, a Representative for East and Central Africa, and later as Deputy Vice President of the International Division. The files include correspondence, interoffice memoranda, grant proposals, papers and reports related to the Foundation's international grant-making. There are also budget files regarding the financial planning and operations of the International Division, records of Dr. Sutton's travels, and copies of speeches and articles written by Dr. Sutton. Also documented is Dr. Sutton's post-retirement work as a consultant on the History Project, an effort he spearheaded for several years.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. Designed to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education through overseas grants, the program initially targeted India and Pakistan, with a more limited number of grants issued in Indonesia and Burma. The Foundation initiated a program for smaller regional and national grants for the Near East region later that same year.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with the International Training and Research and the Population programs, became part of a unified International Division. A subsequent Foundation reorganization in 1983 eliminated the International Division and created two separate program divisions – the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and the Developing Countries Program (DCP).
Biographical / Historical
Francis X. Sutton was born on July 7, 1917 in Oneida, Pennsylvania. In 1938, he graduated from Temple University with a Bachelor of Science in Mathematics. Following his graduation, Dr. Sutton pursued graduate studies in mathematics at Princeton University, where he taught math and earned a Masters degree in 1940. He received a second Masters in Sociology from Harvard University in 1941. While studying in Cambridge, Dr. Sutton taught sociology at Suffolk University. From 1941 through 1945 he served as an aerial navigator and captain in the United States Army Air Force. Dr. Sutton returned to Harvard following the war and earned a PhD in Sociology in 1950. While pursuing his PhD, he was selected as a Junior Fellow of the Society of Fellows of Harvard University. From 1949 through 1954, Dr. Sutton lectured on Social Relations and served as an Assistant Professor in Sociology and General Education at Harvard. He also taught summer courses at Columbia University and the Salzburg Seminar in American Studies.
In July 1954, Dr. Sutton left academia for a position as Executive Associate in the Ford Foundation's Behavioral Sciences Program. He served in this capacity for three years until October 1957 when he became the Program Associate for the Overseas Development program's Near East and Africa division. In July 1963, Dr. Sutton transferred to the East and Central Africa office in Nairobi to serve as the Overseas Development Representative for the region. In February 1967, following the creation of the International Division the previous year, Dr. Sutton became the Assistant to the Vice President and by October 1968 was promoted to Deputy Vice President. Dr. Sutton served as Deputy Vice President throughout the 1970s and early 1980s. In 1977, he was also named Officer in Charge of the European and International Affairs program which formed part of the International Division. Dr. Sutton officially retired from his posts at the Ford Foundation in June 1983 but stayed on as a consultant for several years to compile a history of the Foundation's international work. Dr. Sutton served as Acting Director of the Social Science Research Council (SSRC) for one year, commencing on October 1, 1985. From 1985 through 1992 Dr. Sutton served as both a member and chairman of the SSRC board and a consultant to several organizations and foundations including the Ford Foundation, the World Bank, the Rockefeller Foundation, and USAID.
Related Materials
Ford Foundation Resource Identifier: ACC2001/011 – Developing Countries Program, Office Files of Program Staff, 1960-1983. This collection documents the work of the International Division (later the DCP) in Latin America and Asia from 1960 through 1983, and contains correspondence, memoranda, budget reports and consultant files. (This collection has not yet been received by Rockefeller Archive Center.)
FA530 Ford Foundation records, Education and Culture Program, Office Files of Nancy McCarthy, 1951-1989, 1976-1989 (bulk). Nancy McCarthy joined the Ford Foundation in 1964 and, in 1968, became Dr. Sutton's secretary. In 1978, Ms. McCarthy earned a promotion as Dr. Sutton's research assistant, and throughout the mid-1980s worked with him on his history of the International Division. The collection contains correspondence and memoranda to and from Foundation staff, including Francis X. Sutton, as well as outside consultants and grantees. The files highlight the Foundation's program in International Training and Research. They also draw attention to its work in international studies and language education, and its interest in historically black colleges and refugees and migration trends.
Ford Foundation Resource Identifier: ACC91/17 – Individual Program Officer Correspondence Files, 1968-1987, 1972-1978 (bulk). This collection consists of the outgoing correspondence files of Foundation officers and consultants, and notes and reports prepared by the International Affairs program and its predecessor, European and International Affairs (EIA). The collection contains files belonging to Dr. Sutton from 1977 through 1978, coinciding with his promotion as Officer in Charge of the EIA program. (This collection has not yet been received by Rockefeller Archive Center.)
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Correspondence, 1967-1982
Series II. Program Files, 1952-1985, bulk 1967-1985
Series III. Trip Files, 1957-1980
Series IV. Budget Files, 1966-1983
Series V. Speeches and Articles, 1961-1989
Series VI. Ford Foundation History Project, Regional Files, 1951-1985
Series VII. Ford Foundation History Project, Subject Files, 1949-1985
Series VIII. Researcher Files, 1983-2002, bulk 1985-1987
Series IX. Visual Materials, 1951-1985
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Francis X. Sutton span from 1949-2002 and document his work as a Program Associate, Representative for East and Central Africa, Deputy Vice President of the International Division, and Foundation consultant. The files include correspondence, interoffice memoranda, grant proposals, papers and reports related to the Foundation's international grant-making. There are also budget files regarding the financial planning and operations of the International Division, travel records, and copies of his speeches and articles.
The collection also documents Dr. Sutton's post-retirement work as a Foundation consultant on the History Project. With three decades of Foundation experience in international affairs, Dr. Sutton spearheaded the efforts to assemble materials on and compile a comprehensive account of the Foundation's international policies and work abroad.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
- Correspondence, 1967-1982; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the correspondence files amassed by Dr. Sutton during his tenure in the International Division as Assistant to the Vice President (1967-1968) and Deputy Vice President (1968-1983). The files are arranged chronologically, and then, within each yearly increment, are arranged alphabetically by the surname of the correspondent. The series includes interoffice memoranda sent from and received by Dr. Sutton, as well as correspondence with individuals unaffiliated with the Ford Foundation. The files reveal Dr. Sutton's involvement with the programs and activities under his purview and his opinions and expectations of Foundation work at home and abroad.
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1967 February 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1967 February 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1967 July 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1967 July 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1968 January 1-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1968 January 1-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-M, 1968 May 1-October 31 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, N-Z, 1968 May 1-October 31 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, A-G, 1968 November 1-1969 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, H-Z, 1968 November 1-1969 May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1969 May-October 31 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1969 May-October 31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1969 November 1-1970 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1969 November 1-1970 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1970 June 3-November 30 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, I-Z, 1970 June 3-November 30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-G, 1970 December 1-1971 June 8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, H-P, 1970 December 1-1971 June 8 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, Q-Z, 1970 December 1-1971 June 8 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, A-G, 1971 June 9-1972 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, H-S, 1971 June 9-1972 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, T-Z, 1971 June 9-1972 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1972 February 1-August 9 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1972 February 1-August 9 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1972 August 10-1973 March 31 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, I-Z, 1972 August 10-1973 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1973 April 1-August 6 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1973 April 1-August 6 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1973 August 7-1974 January 10 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1973 August 7-1974 January 10 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1974 January 11-July 19 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, I-Z, 1974 January 11-July 19 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, A-G, 1974 July 20-December 31 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, H-Z, 1974 July 20-December 31 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, A-I, 1975 January 1-June 26 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, J-Z, 1975 January 1-June 26 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1975 June 27-1976 January 13 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1975 June 27-1976 January 13 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-L, 1976 January 14-June 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, M-Z, 1976 January 14-June 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1976 June 2-December 31 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, I-Z, 1976 June 2-December 31 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, A-M, 1977 January 1-May 31 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, N-Z, 1977 January 1-May 31 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-I, 1977 June 1-October 31 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, J-Z, 1977 June 1-October 31 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-N, 1977 November 1-1978 February 28 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, O-Z, 1977 November 1-1978 February 28 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1978 March 1-July 31 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, I-Z, 1978 March 1-July 31 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, A-M, 1978 August 1-December 31 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, N-Z, 1978 August 1-December 31 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1979 January 1-July 31 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, I-R, 1979 January 1-July 31 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, S-Z, 1979 January 1-July 31 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, A-H, 1979 August 1-1980 April 30 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, I-R, 1979 August 1-1980 April 30 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, S-Z, 1979 August 1-1980 April 30 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1980 May 1-October 31 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1980 May 1-October 31 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, A-M, 1980 November 1-1981 March 31 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, N-Z, 1980 November 1-1981 March 31 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1981 April 1-December 31 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1981 April 1-December 31 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, A-K, 1982 January 1-June 15 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, L-Z, 1982 January 1-June 15 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, A-M, 1982 June 16-September 30 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, N-Z, 1982 June 16-September 30 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Program Files, 1952-1985, bulk 1967-1985; 1967-1985; II
  This series contains memoranda, reports, discussion papers, grant proposals, conference and meeting materials, notes, and background information about Foundation activities, grant recipients and events and issues of national and international significance. Dr. Sutton's regional files illustrate the Foundation's work in Africa and the Middle East, Asia and the Pacific, Europe, and Latin America and the Caribbean and the efforts of program officers and staff members both in the New York office and abroad. The files within this series address a myriad of issues, including arts, culture and education, arms control, agriculture, human rights, rural and urban development, employment, women's opportunities, population, and program management.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Affirmative Action -- Background Material, 1975 July 8 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative Action -- Background Material, 1977 March (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Affirmative Action -- Report, 1978 March (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture -- International Agricultural Research -- Papers, 1964-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Agriculture -- International Agricultural Research Centers Review -- Report, Background, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Agriculture -- Resources and Environment (RE) Program Materials -- Memoranda, Notes, Report, Pamphlet Re: RE in Developing Countries, 1967-1976 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Arts, Culture and Education -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Budget Information, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Arts Paper -- Notes, Background Material, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Arts Program Review -- Memoranda, Outlines, Papers, Notes Re: Foundation Arts Program, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Arts Program Review -- Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes, Background (1 of 3), 1981 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Arts Program Review -- Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes, Background (2 of 3), 1981 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Arts Program Review -- Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes, Background (3 of 3), 1981 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Arts Program Review -- Report, "The Arts and Culture in the Ford Foundation", 1981 June (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Memoranda, Reports Re: China Studies and Ford Foundation Work in China and Taiwan (1 of 4), 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Memoranda, Agreements Re: Foundation Relationship with Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS), China Studies, Trips (2 of 4), 1976-1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Memoranda, Reports Re: FF and CASS, Legal Studies and Exchanges, China Meetings and Policy Discussions (3 of 4), 1968-1980, bulk 1979-1980; 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Memoranda, Reports Re: FF and CASS, Academic Exchanges, Legal Studies, Policy Meetings, Country Visits, etc. (4 of 4), 1980-1982 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Report, "The Ford Foundation and the Study of China - Information Paper", 1981 June (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- China -- Report, "Report on a Ford Foundation Rural Economy Team's Visit in China", 1980 October (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- East-Asian Libraries -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes Re: Cooperative Library Ventures and ACLS Study of East Asian Libraries, 1976-1979 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Education in Asia Conference (Singapore, Oct 21-23, 1970) -- Memoranda, Notes, List of Participants, Agenda (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- General -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation Work in Asia and Asian Studies (including Australia and New Zealand) (1 of 4), 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- General -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation Work in Asia and Asian Studies (2 of 4), 1969-1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- General -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation Work in Asia and Asian Studies (3 of 4), 1975-1979 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- General -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation Work in Asia and Asian Studies (4 of 4), 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Japan -- Memoranda, Background Materials, Reports, Notes Re: US-Japan Relations, Foundation Work, Trip Files, Grants, 1967-1980 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Japan -- Report, "Status Report on Japan", 1952 December (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Japan -- Third Japanese-American Conference (April 4-9, 1967) -- Agenda, List of Participants, Reports, Notes, Correspondence, 1967 April (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Malaysia -- Memoranda Re: Argument Against Reducing Foundation Work in Malaysia, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Malaysia -- Report, "The Ford Foundation Program in Malaysia" by John P. Kennedy, 1970 March (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Malaysia -- Report, "The Ford Foundation Program in Malaysia", 1970 August (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Southeast Asia/Malaysia --Reports Re: Economic, Educational, Political Issues, 1976-1982 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Southeast Asia -- Report, "The State of Creative Writing and Problems of Creative Writers in Southeast Asia" by Robert Shaplen, 1979 August (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Vietnam -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation Work and Council on Foreign Relations Vietnam Discussion Group, 1967-1975 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Vietnam -- Report, "Report on an Exploration of Grant-Making Possibilities in Vietnam", 1974 March 1 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - CIA Funded Organizations -- Memoranda, Correspondence Re: FF Response to New York Times Article Re: Asia Foundation (1 of 3), 1968-1982 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - CIA Funded Organizations -- Correspondence, Drafts Re: Ed Berman Article, CIA Orphans (2 of 3), 1968-1979 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - CIA Funded Organizations -- Correspondence Re: FF Response to Ramparts Article (3 of 3), 1967 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Committee on the University and World Affairs -- Report, circa 1961 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Computers -- Memoranda Re: Country Coding and Computer Reporting, Meeting Agenda and Background, 1969-1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- Current Issue Review Group on Domestic Politics in Western Europe -- Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- Current Issue Review Group on the Horn of Africa -- Memoranda, Report, Council Meeting Guidelines, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- Human Rights and U.S. Foreign Policy Discussion Group -- Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes, Reports, 1976-1977 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- Post-Vietnam American Foreign Policy Series -- Meeting Programs and Materials, Reports, Notes, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- Southern Africa and Western Alliance Discussion Group -- Memoranda, Report, Discussion Questions, 1978 April-June (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- "1980s Project-North/South Relations" -- Memoranda, Reports, Project Summaries and Reviews, Membership Information (1 of 4), 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- "1980s Project-North/South Relations" -- April 7, 1976 Meeting Materials -- Memoranda, Notes, Reports, Agenda, Participants List (2 of 4) (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- "1980s Project-North/South Relations" -- April 23, 1976 Meeting Materials -- Notes, Reports, Agenda, Participants List (3 of 4) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Council on Foreign Relations -- "1980s Project-North/South Relations" -- Memoranda Re: Meetings, Project Updates and Publications, Notes (4 of 4), 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Council on Foundations -- Report, "An Assessment for Grantmaking International" by Sheila Avrin McLean, 1982 April (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Employment Study -- Labor Utilization Seminar (June 21, 1971) -- Memoranda, Notes, Discussion Papers (Box 16, Folder 4)